<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data date-time-format="iso8601">
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now become">
    For many states that were once great have now become small; and those that were great in my time were small before.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now the sovereign power that belonged">
    Now the sovereign power that belonged to the descendants of Heracles  fell to the family of Croesus, called the Mermnadae, in the following way.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="ruled for twenty-two generations, or five hundred and five years">
    The Heraclidae, descendants of Heracles and a female slave of Iardanus, received the sovereignty from these and held it, because of an oracle; and they ruled for twenty-two generations, or five hundred and five years, son succeeding father, down to Candaules son of Myrsus.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="addressed him thus: “Now">
    When Gyges came, the lady addressed him thus: “Now, Gyges, you have two ways before you; decide which you will follow.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now without more ado; that will prevent">
    You must either kill Candaules and take me and the throne of Lydia for your own, or be killed yourself now without more ado; that will prevent you from obeying all Candaules' commands in the future and seeing what you should not see.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="reigned for forty-nine years">
    Ardys reigned for forty-nine years and was succeeded by his son Sadyattes, who reigned for twelve years; and after Sadyattes came Alyattes,
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="reigned for twelve years">
    Ardys reigned for forty-nine years and was succeeded by his son Sadyattes, who reigned for twelve years; and after Sadyattes came Alyattes,
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="war in this way for eleven years">
    He waged war in this way for eleven years, and in these years two great disasters overtook the Milesians, one at the battle of Limeneion in their own territory, and the other in the valley of the Maeander.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="years two great disasters overtook">
    He waged war in this way for eleven years, and in these years two great disasters overtook the Milesians, one at the battle of Limeneion in their own territory, and the other in the valley of the Maeander.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="eleven years Sadyattes">
    For six of these eleven years Sadyattes son of Ardys was still ruler of Lydia, and it was he who invaded the lands of Miletus, for it was he who had begun the war; for the following five the war was waged by Sadyattes' son Alyattes, who, as I have indicated before, inherited the war from his father and carried it on vigorously.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="were reduced to the last extremity of misery; but now">
    For Alyattes had supposed that there was great scarcity in Miletus and that the people were reduced to the last extremity of misery; but now on his herald's return from the town he heard an account contrary to his expectations;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="died after a reign of fifty-seven years">
    Alyattes the Lydian, his war with the Milesians finished, died after a reign of fifty-seven years.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the death of Alyattes, his son Croesus, then thirty-five years">
    After the death of Alyattes, his son Croesus, then thirty-five years of age, came to the throne.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="went abroad for ten years">
    and after these were subdued and subject to Croesus in addition to the Lydians, all the sages from Hellas who were living at that time, coming in different ways, came to Sardis, which was at the height of its property; and among them came Solon the Athenian, who, after making laws for the Athenians at their request, went abroad for ten years, sailing forth to see the world, he said.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now I desire">
    After Solon had seen everything and had thought about it, Croesus found the opportunity to say, “My Athenian guest, we have heard a lot about you because of your wisdom and of your wanderings, how as one who loves learning you have traveled much of the world for the sake of seeing it, so now I desire to ask you who is the most fortunate man you have seen.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="set the limit of a man's life at seventy years">
    I set the limit of a man's life at seventy years;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="make every other year longer by one month">
    But if you make every other year longer by one month, so that the seasons agree opportunely, then there are thirty-five intercalary months during the seventy years, and from these months there are one thousand fifty days.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="seasons agree">
    But if you make every other year longer by one month, so that the seasons agree opportunely, then there are thirty-five intercalary months during the seventy years, and from these months there are one thousand fifty days.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the seventy years, all twenty-six thousand, two hundred and fifty of them, not one brings">
    Out of all these days in the seventy years, all twenty-six thousand, two hundred and fifty of them, not one brings anything at all like another.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now while Croesus was occupied">
    Now while Croesus was occupied with the marriage of his son, a Phrygian of the royal house came to Sardis, in great distress and with unclean hands.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now we ask">
    At last they sent messengers to Croesus, with this message: “O King, a great monster of a boar has appeared in the land, who is destroying our fields; for all our attempts, we cannot kill him; so now we ask you to send your son and chosen young men and dogs with us, so that we may drive him out of the country.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now entered">
    But the son of Croesus now entered, having heard what the Mysians had asked for; and when Croesus refused to send his son with them, the young man said,
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="win renown; but now">
    “Father, it was once thought very fine and noble for us to go to war and the chase and win renown; but now you have barred me from both of these, although you have seen neither cowardice nor lack of spirit in me.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now show">
    With what face can I now show myself whenever I go to and from the market-place?
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now then, as you owe">
    Now then, as you owe me a return of good service for the good which I have done you, I ask that you watch over my son as he goes out to the chase.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now, since you urge">
    But now, since you urge it and I must please you (since I owe you a return of good service), I am ready to do this; and as for your son, in so far as I can protect him, look for him to come back unharmed.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now that he was the most heavily afflicted of all whom he knew">
    But Adrastus, son of Gordias who was son of Midas, this Adrastus, the destroyer of his own brother and of the man who purified him, when the tomb was undisturbed by the presence of men, killed himself there by the sepulcher, seeing clearly now that he was the most heavily afflicted of all whom he knew.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="remained in deep sorrow for two years">
    After the loss of his son, Croesus remained in deep sorrow for two years.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now none relate">
    Now none relate what answer was given by the rest of the oracles.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="stood; and now">
    When the temple of Delphi was burnt, this lion fell from the ingots which were the base on which it stood; and now it is in the treasury of the Corinthians, but weighs only six talents and a half, for the fire melted away three and a half talents.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the time of the temple's burning, and now">
    These too were removed about the time of the temple's burning, and now the golden bowl, which weighs eight and a half talents and twelve minae, is in the treasury of the Clazomenians, and the silver bowl at the corner of the forecourt of the temple.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now he asks">
    And now he asks you whether he is to send an army against the Persians, and whether he is to add an army of allies.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="days of king Deucalion it inhabited">
    For in the days of king Deucalion it inhabited the land of Phthia, then the country called Histiaean, under Ossa and Olympus, in the time of Dorus son of Hellen; driven from this Histiaean country by the Cadmeans, it settled about Pindus in the territory called Macedonian; from there again it migrated to Dryopia, and at last came from Dryopia into the Peloponnese, where it took the name of Dorian.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="live above the Tyrrheni in the city of Creston—who were once neighbors of the people now">
    But if one may judge by those that still remain of the Pelasgians who live above the Tyrrheni in the city of Creston—who were once neighbors of the people now called Dorians, and at that time inhabited the country which now is called Thessalian—
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="inhabited the country which now">
    But if one may judge by those that still remain of the Pelasgians who live above the Tyrrheni in the city of Creston—who were once neighbors of the people now called Dorians, and at that time inhabited the country which now is called Thessalian—
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now of these two peoples, Croesus learned">
    Now of these two peoples, Croesus learned that the Attic was held in subjection and divided into factions by Pisistratus, son of Hippocrates, who at that time was sovereign over the Athenians.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="a short time the partisans of Megacles and of Lycurgus made">
    But after a short time the partisans of Megacles and of Lycurgus made common cause and drove him out.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="ten years they set out">
    So after ten years they set out from Eretria and returned home.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="took no notice of it, did now">
    but the Athenians in the city, who while Pisistratus was collecting money and afterwards when he had taken Marathon took no notice of it, did now, and when they learned that he was marching from Marathon against Athens, they set out to attack him.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="declared to him the constitution that now">
    Some say that the Pythia also declared to him the constitution that now exists at Sparta, but the Lacedaemonians themselves say that Lycurgus brought it from Crete when he was guardian of his nephew Leobetes, the Spartan king.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now, so I opened">
    I could not believe that there had ever been men taller than now, so I opened it and saw that the corpse was just as long as the coffin.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now, therefore, since I learn">
    “Croesus, King of Lydia and other nations, has sent us with this message: ‘Lacedaemonians, the god has declared that I should make the Greek my friend; now, therefore, since I learn that you are the leaders of Hellas, I invite you, as the oracle bids; I would like to be your friend and ally, without deceit or guile.’”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now stands">
    For the Lacedaemonians had sent to Sardis to buy gold, intending to use it for the statue of Apollo which now stands on Thornax in Laconia; and Croesus, when they offered to buy it, made them a free gift of it.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="was already held to be a wise man, and who, from the advice which he now">
    But while he was preparing to march against the Persians, a certain Lydian, who was already held to be a wise man, and who, from the advice which he now gave, won a great name among the Lydians, advised him as follows (his name was Sandanis): “O King, you are getting ready to march against men who wear trousers of leather and whose complete wardrobe is of leather, and who eat not what they like but what they have; for their land is stony.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now if you conquer">
    Now if you conquer them, of what will you deprive them, since they have nothing?
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now the Cappadocians are called">
    Now the Cappadocians are called by the Greeks Syrians, and these Syrians before the Persian rule were subjects of the Medes, and, at this time, of Cyrus.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now Astyages, son of Cyaxares and the king of Media, was Croesus' brother-in-law: and this is how he came">
    Now Astyages, son of Cyaxares and the king of Media, was Croesus' brother-in-law: and this is how he came to be so.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="war between the Lydians and the Medes for five years">
    After this, since Alyattes would not give up the Scythians to Cyaxares at his demand, there was war between the Lydians and the Medes for five years; each won many victories over the other, and once they fought a battle by night.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="a long time, again sent">
    But Croesus, supposing that the siege would last a long time, again sent messengers from the city to his allies; whereas the former envoys had been sent to summon them to muster at Sardis in five months' time, these were to announce that Croesus was besieged and to plead for help as quickly as possible.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now at this very time the Spartans themselves were feuding">
    Now at this very time the Spartans themselves were feuding with the Argives over the country called Thyrea;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="wear their hair long ever after; for until now">
    and the Lacedaemonians made a contrary law, that they wear their hair long ever after; for until now they had not worn it so.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now besieged">
    The Sardian herald came after this had happened to the Spartans to ask for their help for Croesus, now besieged; nonetheless, when they heard the herald, they prepared to send help; but when they were already equipped and their ships ready, a second message came that the fortification of the Lydians was taken and Croesus a prisoner.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="had been besieged for fourteen days">
    When Croesus had been besieged for fourteen days, Cyrus sent horsemen around in his army to promise to reward whoever first mounted the wall.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="The day before, then, Hyroeades, this Mardian, had seen">
    The day before, then, Hyroeades, this Mardian, had seen one of the Lydians come down by this part of the acropolis after a helmet that had fallen down, and fetch it; he took note of this and considered it.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now he climbed up">
    And now he climbed up himself, and other Persians after him.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="will now">
    I will now relate what happened to Croesus himself.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="remain mute as before; For on an unlucky day">
    It were better for you that he remain mute as before;
For on an unlucky day shall he first speak.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="had ruled fourteen years">
    Croesus had ruled fourteen years and been besieged fourteen days.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now everything had turned out">
    Now everything had turned out for him as Solon had said, speaking no more of him than of every human being, especially those who think themselves fortunate.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now, or keep">
    Presently he turned and said (for he saw the Persians sacking the city of the Lydians), “O King, am I to say to you what is in my mind now, or keep silent?”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="said: “Croesus, now">
    When Cyrus heard this, he was exceedingly pleased, for he believed the advice good; and praising him greatly, and telling his guard to act as Croesus had advised, he said: “Croesus, now that you, a king, are determined to act and to speak with integrity, ask me directly for whatever favor you like.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="delayed the taking of Sardis for three years">
    Yet as far as they gave in, he did accomplish his wish and favor Croesus: for he delayed the taking of Sardis for three years.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="know this: that although he is now">
    And let Croesus know this: that although he is now taken, it is by so many years later than the destined hour.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="taken, it is by so many years later">
    And let Croesus know this: that although he is now taken, it is by so many years later than the destined hour.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="make further inquiry: for which now">
    But he did not understood what was spoken, or make further inquiry: for which now let him blame himself.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now this tomb has a circumference of thirteen hundred and ninety yards, and its breadth is above four hundred and forty yards; and there is a great lake hard by the tomb, which, the Lydians say">
    Now this tomb has a circumference of thirteen hundred and ninety yards, and its breadth is above four hundred and forty yards; and there is a great lake hard by the tomb, which, the Lydians say, is fed by ever-flowing springs; it is called the Gygaean lake.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the games now">
    And, according to what they themselves say, the games now in use among them and the Greeks were invented by the Lydians: these, they say, were invented among them at the time when they colonized Tyrrhenia.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the next day they quit">
    Then, using their discovery to lighten the famine, every other day they would play for the whole day, so that they would not have to look for food, and the next day they quit their play and ate.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="had ruled Upper Asia for five hundred and twenty years">
    After the Assyrians had ruled Upper Asia for five hundred and twenty years, the Medes were the first who began to revolt from them.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now free men; but they came">
    All of those on the mainland were now free men; but they came to be ruled by monarchs again, as I will now relate.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="will now">
    All of those on the mainland were now free men; but they came to be ruled by monarchs again, as I will now relate.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now depended">
    Then Deioces, seeing that everything now depended on him, would not sit in his former seat of judgment, and said he would give no more decisions; for it was of no advantage to him (he said) to leave his own business and spend all day judging the cases of his neighbors.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="built the big and strong walls, one standing inside the next in circles, which are now">
    So he built the big and strong walls, one standing inside the next in circles, which are now called Ecbatana.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="built these walls for himself and around his own quarters">
    Deioces built these walls for himself and around his own quarters, and he ordered the people to dwell outside the wall.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="died after a reign of fifty-three years">
    Deioces had a son, Phraortes, who inherited the throne when Deioces died after a reign of fifty-three years.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now their allies had deserted">
    These had formerly been rulers of all; but now their allies had deserted them and they were left alone, though well-off themselves.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="had reigned twenty-two years">
    Marching against these Assyrians, then, Phraortes and most of his army perished, after he had reigned twenty-two years.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="ruled Asia for twenty-eight years">
    The Scythians, then, ruled Asia for twenty-eight years: and the whole land was ruined because of their violence and their pride, for, besides exacting from each the tribute which was assessed, they rode about the land carrying off everyone's possessions.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="died after a reign of forty years">
    Afterwards, Cyaxares died after a reign of forty years (among which I count the years of the Scythian domination) and his son Astyages inherited the sovereignty.Astyages had a daughter, whom he called Mandane: he dreamed that she urinated so much that she filled his city and flooded all of Asia.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="count the years">
    Afterwards, Cyaxares died after a reign of forty years (among which I count the years of the Scythian domination) and his son Astyages inherited the sovereignty.Astyages had a daughter, whom he called Mandane: he dreamed that she urinated so much that she filled his city and flooded all of Asia.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now, then,” she said">
    “Now, then,” she said to him, “what do you propose to do?” “Not to obey Astyages' instructions,” he answered, “not even if he should lose his mind and be more frantic than he is now: I will not lend myself to his plan or be an accessory to such a murder.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now: I will not lend">
    “Now, then,” she said to him, “what do you propose to do?” “Not to obey Astyages' instructions,” he answered, “not even if he should lose his mind and be more frantic than he is now: I will not lend myself to his plan or be an accessory to such a murder.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now if the sovereignty passes">
    Now if the sovereignty passes to this daughter of his after his death, whose son he is now killing by means of me, what is left for me but the gravest of all dangers?
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="his death, whose son he is now">
    Now if the sovereignty passes to this daughter of his after his death, whose son he is now killing by means of me, what is left for me but the gravest of all dangers?
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now as it happened">
    Now as it happened his wife too had been on the verge of delivering every day, and as the divinity would have it, she did in fact give birth while the cowherd was away in the city.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now, here he is.">
    And now, here he is.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="ten years old, the truth about him was revealed">
    Now when the boy was ten years old, the truth about him was revealed in some such way as this.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="was playing in the village where these herdsmen's quarters">
    He was playing in the village where these herdsmen's quarters were, playing in the road with others of his age.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now, if I deserve">
    Now, if I deserve punishment for this, here I am to take it.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now, then, in this good turn of fortune, send">
    Now, then, in this good turn of fortune, send your own son to this boy newly come, and (since I am about to sacrifice for the boy's safety to the gods to whom this honor is due) come here to dine with me.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="told his only son, a boy of about thirteen years">
    Coming in, he told his only son, a boy of about thirteen years of age, to go to Astyages' palace and do whatever the king commanded, and in his great joy he told his wife everything that had happened.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now the dream has had a trifling conclusion, and we ourselves are confident and advise">
    And if at the present time we saw any danger we would declare everything to you: but now the dream has had a trifling conclusion, and we ourselves are confident and advise you to be so also.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="live; now">
    Hearing this, Astyages was glad, and calling Cyrus, said, “My boy, I did you wrong because of a vision I had in a dream, that meant nothing, but by your own destiny you still live; now therefore, go to the Persians, and good luck go with you; I will send guides with you.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="said that until now">
    Then he told them, and said that until now he had known nothing but been very deceived, but that on the way he had heard the whole story of his misfortune; for he had thought, he said, that Astyages' cowherd was his father, but in his journey from the city his escort had told him the whole story.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="avenge yourself now">
    Cyrus took the hare and slit it and read the paper which was in it; the writing was as follows: “Son of Cambyses, since the gods watch over you (otherwise you would not have prospered so) avenge yourself now on Astyages, your murderer;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now ruled">
    If, then, you will listen to me, you shall rule all the country which is now ruled by Astyages.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now,” he said">
    “Now,” he said in his speech, “I command you, men of Persia, to come, each provided with a sickle.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now there are many tribes in Persia: those of them that Cyrus assembled and persuaded">
    Now there are many tribes in Persia: those of them that Cyrus assembled and persuaded to revolt from the Medes were the Pasargadae, the Maraphii, and the Maspii.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="come the next day">
    The Persians accomplished the task appointed; Cyrus then commanded them to wash themselves and come the next day; meanwhile, collecting his father's goats and sheep and oxen in one place, he slaughtered and prepared them as a feast for the Persian host, providing also wine and all the foods that were most suitable.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="came on the next day">
    When the Persians came on the next day he had them sit and feast in a meadow.
  </event>
  <event start="2016-02-23T00:00:00Z" title="liked more: their task of yesterday">
    After dinner he asked them which they liked more: their task of yesterday or their present pastime.
  </event>
  <event start="2016-02-23T00:00:00Z" title="answered that the difference was great: all yesterday">
    They answered that the difference was great: all yesterday they had had nothing but evil, to-day nothing but good.
  </event>
  <event start="2016-02-23T00:00:00Z" title="will have labors unnumbered like your toil of yesterday">
    “This is your situation, men of Persia: obey me and you shall have these good things and ten thousand others besides with no toil and slavery; but if you will not obey me, you will have labors unnumbered like your toil of yesterday.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now, then, do as I tell">
    Now, then, do as I tell you, and win your freedom.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="ruled them, and now">
    The Persians had long been discontent that the Medes ruled them, and now having got a champion they were glad to win their freedom.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="slaves instead of masters and the Persians, who were the slaves, are now">
    For if in any event another and not you had to possess the royal power, then in justice some Mede should have had it, not a Persian: but now you have made the Medes, who did you no harm, slaves instead of masters and the Persians, who were the slaves, are now the masters of the Medes.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="was deposed from his sovereignty after a reign of thirty-five years">
    Thus Astyages was deposed from his sovereignty after a reign of thirty-five years: and the Medes had to bow down before the Persians because of Astyages' cruelty.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="had ruled all Asia beyond the Halys for one hundred and twenty-eight years">
    They had ruled all Asia beyond the Halys for one hundred and twenty-eight years, from which must be subtracted the time when the Scythians held sway.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="repented of what they now">
    At a later time they repented of what they now did, and rebelled against Darius ; but they were defeated in battle and brought back into subjection.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now, in Astyages' time, Cyrus and the Persians rose">
    But now, in Astyages' time, Cyrus and the Persians rose in revolt against the Medes, and from this time ruled Asia.
  </event>
  <event start="2016-02-24T00:00:00Z" title="this day, he thinks">
    On this day, he thinks it right to serve a more abundant meal than on other days: oxen or horses or camels or asses, roasted whole in ovens, are set before the rich; the poorer serve the lesser kinds of cattle.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="days: oxen or horses or camels or asses, roasted">
    On this day, he thinks it right to serve a more abundant meal than on other days: oxen or horses or camels or asses, roasted whole in ovens, are set before the rich; the poorer serve the lesser kinds of cattle.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="is proposed to them the next day">
    and what they approve in their deliberations is proposed to them the next day, when they are sober, by the master of the house where they deliberate; and if, being sober, they still approve it, they act on it, but if not, they drop it.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="educate their boys from five to twenty years">
    They educate their boys from five to twenty years old, and teach them only three things: riding and archery and honesty.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="is not seen by his father before he is five years">
    A boy is not seen by his father before he is five years old, but lives with the women: the point of this is that, if the boy should die in the interval of his rearing, the father would suffer no grief.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="return now">
    Leaving this custom to be such as it has been from the first, I return now to my former story.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="stop your dancing now">
    Disappointed of his hope, he cast a net and gathered it in and took out a great multitude of fish; and seeing them leaping, “You had best,” he said, “stop your dancing now; you would not come out and dance before, when I played to you.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now these Ionians possessed">
    Now these Ionians possessed the Panionion, and of all men whom we know, they happened to found their cities in places with the loveliest of climate and seasons.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="found their cities in places with the loveliest of climate and seasons">
    Now these Ionians possessed the Panionion, and of all men whom we know, they happened to found their cities in places with the loveliest of climate and seasons.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="spurned the name; even now">
    Now the Athenians and the rest would not be called Ionians, but spurned the name; even now the greater number of them seem to me to be ashamed of it; but the twelve cities aforesaid gloried in this name, and founded a holy place for themselves which they called the Panionion, and agreed among themselves to allow no other Ionians to use it (nor in fact did any except the men of Smyrna ask to be admitted);
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now the country of the “Five Cities”—formerly the country of the “Six Cities”—forbid">
    just as the Dorians of what is now the country of the “Five Cities”—formerly the country of the “Six Cities”—forbid admitting any of the neighboring Dorians to the Triopian temple, and even barred from using it those of their own group who had broken the temple law.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now when a man of Halicarnassus called">
    Now when a man of Halicarnassus called Agasicles won, he disregarded this law, and, carrying the tripod away, nailed it to the wall of his own house.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="battle by the Achaeans; Aegion; Rhype; Patrae; Phareae; and Olenus, where is the great river Pirus; Dyme and Tritaeae, the only inland city of all these—these were the twelve divisions of the Ionians, as they are now">
    As for the Ionians, the reason why they made twelve cities and would admit no more was in my judgment this: there were twelve divisions of them when they dwelt in the Peloponnese, just as there are twelve divisions of the Achaeans who drove the Ionians out—Pellene nearest to Sicyon; then Aegira and Aegae, where is the never-failing river Crathis, from which the river in Italy took its name; Bura and Helice, where the Ionians fled when they were worsted in battle by the Achaeans; Aegion; Rhype; Patrae; Phareae; and Olenus, where is the great river Pirus; Dyme and Tritaeae, the only inland city of all these—these were the twelve divisions of the Ionians, as they are now of the Achaeans.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now this is how the Aeolians lost">
    Now this is how the Aeolians lost Smyrna.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now made">
    This man was now made general by Cyrus.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="ruled Tartessus for eighty years">
    When they came to Tartessus they made friends with the king of the Tartessians, whose name was Arganthonius; he ruled Tartessus for eighty years and lived a hundred and twenty.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="had built a city called Alalia twenty years before">
    The Phocaeans would have bought the islands called Oenussae from the Chians; but the Chians would not sell them, because they feared that the islands would become a market and so their own island be cut off from trade: so the Phocaeans prepared to sail to Cyrnus, where at the command of an oracle they had built a city called Alalia twenty years before.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="lived there for five years">
    And when they came to Cyrnus they lived there for five years as one community with those who had come first, and they founded temples there.
  </event>
  <event start="2016-02-24T00:00:00Z" title="told them to do what the people of Agylla do to this day">
    The Agyllaeans sent to Delphi, wanting to mend their offense; and the Pythian priestess told them to do what the people of Agylla do to this day: for they pay great honors to the Phocaeans, with religious rites and games and horse-races.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="possession of that city in the Oenotrian country which is now">
    Those of them who fled to Rhegium set out from there and gained possession of that city in the Oenotrian country which is now called Hyele;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now honored">
    This Timesius is now honored as a hero by the Teians of Abdera.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="a long time afterwards, the Carians were driven">
    Then, a long time afterwards, the Carians were driven from the islands by Dorians and Ionians and so came to the mainland.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="bear now">
    This is the Cretan story about the Carians; but the Carians themselves do not subscribe to it, but believe that they are aboriginal inhabitants of the mainland and always bore the name which they bear now;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="ancient times (for in the past">
    The Lycians were from Crete in ancient times (for in the past none that lived on Crete were Greek).
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now there was a dispute in Crete about the royal power between Sarpedon and Minos, sons of Europa; Minos prevailed">
    Now there was a dispute in Crete about the royal power between Sarpedon and Minos, sons of Europa; Minos prevailed in this dispute and drove out Sarpedon and his partisans; who, after being driven out, came to the Milyan land in Asia.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now possessed">
    What is now possessed by the Lycians was in the past Milyan, and the Milyans were then called Solymi.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now while Harpagus was conquering">
    Now while Harpagus was conquering Ionia, the Cnidians dug a trench across this little space, which is about two-thirds of a mile wide, in order that their country might be an island.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="claim now">
    Of the Xanthians who claim now to be Lycians the greater number, all except eighty households, are of foreign descent; these eighty families as it happened were away from the city at that time, and thus survived.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="will now">
    Babylon was a city such as I will now describe.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Is, eight days">
    There is another city, called Is, eight days' journey from Babylon, where there is a little river, also named Is, a tributary of the Euphrates river; from the source of this river Is, many lumps of bitumen rise with the water; and from there the bitumen was brought for the wall of Babylon.
  </event>
  <event start="2016-02-24T00:00:00Z" title="surrounded by a high and strong wall; and in the middle of the other is still to this day">
    In the middle of one division of the city stands the royal palace, surrounded by a high and strong wall; and in the middle of the other is still to this day the sacred enclosure of Zeus Belus, a square of four hundred and forty yards each way, with gates of bronze.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="keep the festival of this god; and in the days">
    There is also another great altar, on which are sacrificed the full-grown of the flocks; only nurslings may be sacrificed on the golden altar, but on the greater altar the Chaldeans even offer a thousand talents' weight of frankincense yearly, when they keep the festival of this god; and in the days of Cyrus there was still in this sacred enclosure a statue of solid gold twenty feet high.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="crooked that its course now">
    First she dealt with the river Euphrates, which flows through the middle of her city; this had been straight before; but by digging canals higher up she made the river so crooked that its course now passes one of the Assyrian villages three times; the village which is so approached by the Euphrates is called Ardericca.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now those who travel">
    And now those who travel from our sea to Babylon must spend three days as they float down the Euphrates coming three times to the same village.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="three days as they float">
    And now those who travel from our sea to Babylon must spend three days as they float down the Euphrates coming three times to the same village.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="days of the former rulers, when one wanted">
    In the days of the former rulers, when one wanted to go from one part to the other, one had to cross in a boat; and this, I suppose, was a nuisance.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="was filling, the former channel now">
    She had very long blocks of stone cut; and when these were ready and the place was dug, she turned the course of the river into it, and while it was filling, the former channel now being dry, she bricked the borders of the river in the city and the descent from the gate leading down to the river with baked bricks, like those of the wall; and near the middle of the city she built a bridge with the stones that had been dug up, binding them together with iron and lead.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the future is in need of money, let">
    “If any king of Babylon in the future is in need of money, let him open this tomb and take as much as he likes: but let him not open it unless he is in need; for it will be the worse for him.”
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now when the Great King campaigns, he marches">
    Now when the Great King campaigns, he marches well provided with food and flocks from home; and water from the Choaspes river that flows past Susa is carried with him, the only river from which the king will drink.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="spent the whole summer">
    Since a great multitude was at work, it went quickly; but they spent the whole summer there before it was finished.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the beginning of the following spring, when Cyrus had punished">
    Then at the beginning of the following spring, when Cyrus had punished the Gyndes by dividing it among the three hundred and sixty canals, he marched against Babylon at last.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="had stored provisions enough for very many years">
    There they had stored provisions enough for very many years, because they knew already that Cyrus was not a man of no ambitition, and saw that he attacked all nations alike; so now they were indifferent to the siege; and Cyrus did not know what to do, being so long delayed and gaining no advantage.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="attacked all nations alike; so now">
    There they had stored provisions enough for very many years, because they knew already that Cyrus was not a man of no ambitition, and saw that he attacked all nations alike; so now they were indifferent to the siege; and Cyrus did not know what to do, being so long delayed and gaining no advantage.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="made their way into Babylon by the channel of the Euphrates, which had now">
    When this happened, the Persians who were posted with this objective made their way into Babylon by the channel of the Euphrates, which had now sunk to a depth of about the middle of a man's thigh.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now if the Babylonians had known">
    Now if the Babylonians had known beforehand or learned what Cyrus was up to, they would have let the Persians enter the city and have destroyed them utterly; for then they would have shut all the gates that opened on the river and mounted the walls that ran along the river banks, and so caught their enemies in a trap.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="pays tribute besides: now">
    All the land that the great King rules is parcelled out to provision him and his army, and pays tribute besides: now the territory of Babylon feeds him for four of the twelve months in the year, the whole of the rest of Asia providing for the other eight.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="feeds him for four of the twelve months">
    All the land that the great King rules is parcelled out to provision him and his army, and pays tribute besides: now the territory of Babylon feeds him for four of the twelve months in the year, the whole of the rest of Asia providing for the other eight.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="rises in winter">
    The greatest of these is navigable: it runs towards where the sun rises in winter, from the Euphrates to another river, the Tigris, on which stood the city of Ninus.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="will now">
    I will now speak of their established customs.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="a year in every village all the maidens as they attained">
    It is this: once a year in every village all the maidens as they attained marriageable age were collected and brought together into one place, with a crowd of men standing around.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="come now">
    I come now to the next wisest of their customs: having no use for physicians, they carry the sick into the market-place; then those who have been afflicted themselves by the same illness as the sick man's, or seen others in like case, come near and advise him about his disease and comfort him, telling him by what means they have themselves recovered from it or seen others recover.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="remain for three years">
    So then the women that are fair and tall are soon free to depart, but the uncomely have long to wait because they cannot fulfill the law; for some of them remain for three years, or four.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="is reported that there are many islands in it as big as Lesbos, and men on them who in summer">
    It is reported that there are many islands in it as big as Lesbos, and men on them who in summer live on roots of all kinds that they dig up, and in winter on fruit that they have got from trees when it was ripe and stored for food;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="dig up, and in winter">
    It is reported that there are many islands in it as big as Lesbos, and men on them who in summer live on roots of all kinds that they dig up, and in winter on fruit that they have got from trees when it was ripe and stored for food;
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now at this time the Massagetae were ruled">
    Now at this time the Massagetae were ruled by a queen called Tomyris, whose husband was dead.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="withdraw three days">
    But if you will not take this advice, and will do anything rather than remain at peace, then if you so greatly desire to try the strength of the Massagetae, stop your present work of bridging the river, and let us withdraw three days' journey from the Araxes; and when that is done, cross into our country.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="now heard">
    “O King,” he said, “you have before now heard from me that since Zeus has given me to you I will turn aside to the best of my ability whatever misadventure I see threatening your house.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now, if you think">
    Now, if you think that you and the army that you lead are immortal, I have no business giving you advice; but if you know that you and those whom you rule are only men, then I must first teach you this: men's fortunes are on a wheel, which in its turning does not allow the same man to prosper forever.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now then, it occurs">
    Now then, it occurs to me that we should cross and go forward as far as they draw back, and that then we should endeavor to overcome them by doing as I shall show.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="about twenty years old; this Darius had been left">
    Hystaspes son of Arsames was an Achaemenid, and Darius was the eldest of his sons, then about twenty years old; this Darius had been left behind in Persia, not yet being of an age to go on campaign.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="a day's journey from the Araxes, acted">
    After having given this answer and crossed the Araxes, Hystaspes went to Persia to watch his son for Cyrus; and Cyrus, advancing a day's journey from the Araxes, acted according to Croesus' advice.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now, then, take">
    Now, then, take a word of good advice from me: give me back my son and leave this country unpunished, even though you have savaged a third of the Massagetae army.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="fought with their spears and swords; and for a long time">
    For first (it is said) they shot arrows at each other from a distance; then, when their arrows were all spent, they rushed at each other and fought with their spears and swords; and for a long time they stood fighting and neither would give ground; but at last the Massagetae got the upper hand.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="Now for their customs: each man marries">
    Now for their customs: each man marries a wife, but the wives are common to all.
  </event>
</data>
