<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data date-time-format="iso8601">
  <event start="2015-03-15T00:00:00Z" title="Sunday 22 – expect">
    Leicester is filling up with yellow road signs, warning of the return of the once and future king: "King Richard III Route Sunday 22 – expect delays".
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="more than two years since the bones rediscovered">
    It is more than two years since the bones rediscovered by archaeologists under a council car park in the heart of Leicester, were formally identified as those of the last Plantagenet king.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="several days after his death at Bosworth, he was buried">
    In the heat of August, several days after his death at Bosworth, he was buried hastily in a roughly-dug grave slightly too small for his naked body.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="This time a week">
    This time a week of events will surround the reinterment on Thursday 26 in the cathedral – delayed for a year by a legal challenge claiming that he should have been buried in York – including a procession on Sunday through the countryside associated with the last days of the last Plantagenet, led by two knights in armour on horseback.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-03-19T00:00:00Z" title="will surround the reinterment on Thursday">
    This time a week of events will surround the reinterment on Thursday 26 in the cathedral – delayed for a year by a legal challenge claiming that he should have been buried in York – including a procession on Sunday through the countryside associated with the last days of the last Plantagenet, led by two knights in armour on horseback.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="delayed for a year">
    This time a week of events will surround the reinterment on Thursday 26 in the cathedral – delayed for a year by a legal challenge claiming that he should have been buried in York – including a procession on Sunday through the countryside associated with the last days of the last Plantagenet, led by two knights in armour on horseback.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-03-15T00:00:00Z" title="Sunday through the countryside associated">
    This time a week of events will surround the reinterment on Thursday 26 in the cathedral – delayed for a year by a legal challenge claiming that he should have been buried in York – including a procession on Sunday through the countryside associated with the last days of the last Plantagenet, led by two knights in armour on horseback.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="days of the last Plantagenet, led">
    This time a week of events will surround the reinterment on Thursday 26 in the cathedral – delayed for a year by a legal challenge claiming that he should have been buried in York – including a procession on Sunday through the countryside associated with the last days of the last Plantagenet, led by two knights in armour on horseback.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="created behind the altar, where purple drapes now">
    Beautiful red sandstone slabs, inset with four small white stone roses, have been laid in the new space created behind the altar, where purple drapes now cover a brick-lined pit ready to receive the coffin.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-03-22T00:00:00Z" title="will stop on Sunday afternoon">
    In the village of Sutton Cheney representatives of the local council, the highways authority, the cathedral, villagers, the vicar and churchwardens, gathered to measure with a stop watch every second of the ten minutes the cortege will stop on Sunday afternoon on its slow way to the cathedral.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="battle, now">
    A country lane leads from the village street to Ambion Hill, where Richard's troops are believed to have camped on the eve of battle, now the site of the Bosworth Battlefield Heritage Centre where a major open air ceremony will be led by the Tim Stevens, the bishop of Leicester.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-03-08T00:00:00Z" title="went online 10 days ago">
    When tickets went online 10 days ago, the website crashed within minutes: every member of staff came in to deal by phone with thousands of enquiries.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the future Henry VII, lost">
    The churchyard at Dadlington gives a panoramic view of the entire battle landscape, from Ambion Hill to the marshy corner of a field at Fen Lane, several miles away, where Richard lost his horse in a last desperate charging attempt to kill the future Henry VII, lost his crown and his helmet, and then lost his life to two savage blows to the base of his skull.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="the 1950s, pits of bones were found">
    On at least three occasions in the last two centuries, most recently in the 1950s, pits of bones were found as graves were being dug for village funerals.
  </event>
  <event start="0000-00-00T00:00:00Z" title="an entire day of events, centred">
    After the cortege passes through, the tiny village has organised an entire day of events, centred on the village green and hall – which they decided last month was looking unacceptably shabby and within a fortnight, using local volunteers and donated materials, completely redecorated inside and out.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-02-01T00:00:00Z" end="2015-02-28T00:00:00Z" isDuration="true" title="decided last month">
    After the cortege passes through, the tiny village has organised an entire day of events, centred on the village green and hall – which they decided last month was looking unacceptably shabby and within a fortnight, using local volunteers and donated materials, completely redecorated inside and out.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-03-14T00:00:00Z" title="Saturday night, put">
    Dadlington usually divides its sympathies between the two sides, but the villagers have already packed the church on a Saturday night, put Richard on trial for the murder of his nephews, the Little Princes in the Tower, and found him not guilty: "you may leave without a stain on your character," Jacqui Morton, a former banker acting as judge for the night, assured him.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-03-22T00:00:00Z" title="Sunday will only fly">
    The battlefield centre usually flies the standards of both Richard and Henry Tudor – "without wanting to appear like the Stanleys", Mackinder said, of Richard's former ally who lurked on the fringes of the battle until he saw which way the wind was blowing and then threw in his forces with the Tudors, "we usually have to sit on the fence a bit" – but on Sunday will only fly Richard's.
  </event>
  <event start="2014-08-01T00:00:00Z" end="2014-08-31T00:00:00Z" isDuration="true" title="the battle every August">
    At Sutton Cheney, on the anniversary of the battle every August, churchwarden Mary Burgess includes a little red posy with the white flowers she lays for Richard, to remember the dead of both sides.
  </event>
  <event start="2015-03-22T00:00:00Z" title="Sunday we'll have">
    "But on Sunday we'll have white flowers only," she said.
  </event>
</data>
